[Music]
Stanford University.
Okay.
So, vermionic strings have been a part
of the subject since almost the
beginning, not quite the
beginning. And as I said, they solve two
important problems. I forgot what they
are though. Oh, they give you
firmians and they get rid of the
tachons.
they leave you with 10 dimensions
instead of 26. So they don't solve that
problem. That problem turned out to be
less of a problem and more of a feature.
Feature means a good feature than people
had expected at the time.
Uh but we'll come to it and it's a
subject known as
compactification. Taking the extra
dimensions and doing something with them
to make them innocuous.
uh or if not innocuous an interesting
feature of the theory but we'll come to
that not now though what I wanted to
talk about a little bit was not really
historical but uh the scattering of
strings the subject really
began with studying scattering of
particles elementary particle physics
was always about scattering ing of
particles. Not because it's the most
interesting phenomena that can happen.
It's not. It's rather dull. You send
some particles together and a bunch of
junk comes out in all sorts of
directions. But it's about all we can do
in the way of experiment. And so we try
to unravel from the scattering uh data
what was going on inside the collision
and inside the collision of course means
the properties of particles and so
forth. So the natural um
tool of experiment the scattering and
the natural thing that a theorist would
ask is if I have a theory of
particles how do you compute the
scattering amplitudes? The scattering
amplitudes what is a scattering
amplitude? The scattering amplitude you
have some incoming particles that are
part of your incoming information. I'm
going to have time running this way
tonight.
horizontally instead of vertically. I
don't know why.
Variety particles come
in, something happens inside a black
box and particles go out. Not
necessarily the same number of
particles. The particles come in and
they carry momentum. Of course, they
carry other things. They carry spin.
They carry charge. They carry labels.
Like for example, is it a muon or is it
a
uh whatever it happens to be? But let's
simplify the story and ignore everything
except their momentum. So particles come
in and they carry for momentum. For
momentum means energy and momentum.
Okay, let's write down what a four
vector of energy momentum
is. the energy and the three components
of
momentum. Of course, if we're working in
26 dimensions, we have 25 components
here, but I'll just write down four of
them. That's a four vector, relativistic
for vector. Each particle has a
momentum, and we're going to call it K.
K mu where mu goes from 1 to
four from 0ero to four excuse from 0 to
three this is usually called 0 1 2 3
doesn't matter four components of
momentum now what do we know about the
components the four components of
momentum of a
particle they have something to do with
the mass of the particle well of course
they are the energy and the momentum
what's the relationship between energy
and momentum and mass S for a
relativistic particle anybody remember C
is one we will take C = H bar = 1 what's
the connection between the components of
energy momentum and
mass
E2 E2
= P ^2 +
M^2 or let's write it the following
way e^2 2 minus p ^2 =
m^2. And just in order to keep my cons
my notation consistent
with notations of physicists for many
many years I am going to write this as
p^2 minus
e^2= minus m^2. Same formula I've just
taken the negative of it.
Now that can also be written in terms of
the components of
K. In terms of the components of K
that's what is it? It's KN squared.
Sorry, it's uh K vector squared minus KN
squared. KN standing for the time
component E spatial component squared
minus the time component squared. And
this is often just called K squared.
just call it k^ squ. The left hand side
here is the
square by definition. It's a definition
of the relativistic square of a vector.
It's called p mu p
mu. Or to simplify it, let's just call
it k
squ. It's the space component squared
minus the time component squared. That's
called k squ. And for every
particle k^2 is equal to minus
m^2. You can't vary
k^2. Of course k^ squ consists of the
energy and the momentum. When you say
you can't vary k^ squ it doesn't mean
you can't vary the momentum. It means
when you vary the momentum the energy
varies in a certain way. And the way
that it varies is that E^2 minus P^2 or
K * K^ 2 minus K space 2= minus M^2. So
that's the first
thing about it's not even about
collisions. It's just about particles.
You characterize them by their for
momentum. Three components of which are
independent. The fourth component has to
be subject to this constraint. Now we
put in a bunch of momenta. Let's call
this K1 for the first
particle. Is that the way I label them?
I like to keep my notation
straight. Yeah, I think I call this one
K1. This one K2. And then outgoing over
here, we'll call the incoming momenta K.
I'm going to call the outgoing momenta
Q. These are also for momenta want to
call it Q3 Q4 dot dot dot. Let's take
the very simple case in which two
particles go to two
particles.
Q4 these particles come in those
particles go out. How do you represent
momentum conservation? Momentum and
energy conservation. Momentum and energy
conservation are simply that K1 + K2
thought of as four vectors is equal to
Q3 +
Q4. All components the space components
define momentum conservation. The time
components define energy
conservation. Okay. Now because of the
perversity of physicists, what
physicists like to do is to redefine the
outgoing
momentum and think of them as incoming
momentum. Now that's crazy. The outgoing
momentum are outgoing, the incoming
momentum are incoming. But to do it, all
we really have to do to make it
symmetric with respect to incoming and
outgoing momentum, just take each
Q4, change its sign and call it
K minus
K3. That means changing the sign of its
energy, means changing the sign of all
of its momentum. It's it's a it's a
trick to be able to write this in a
symmetric form. Instead of writing K1
well, let's see what it is. It's here's
what it
is. K1 + K2 minus Q 4 minus Q3 equals Z.
Now becomes K1 + K2 + K3 + K4 equals Z.
You treat all particles as
incoming. But you have to remember that
the label for the outgoing particles is
labeled with minus the actual momentum
of the outgoing particle. But once you
do so, momentum conservation is
completely symmetric between the four
between the four particles. A useful
trick. It's a useful trick that uh
that keeps
labeling especially
consistent. Notice that when you change
the sign of the momentum to redefine the
momentum with a minus sign, it does not
change the fact that the square of the
momentum is equal to minus m^2. So we
have in this particular process we have
four momenta. Think of them as all
incoming although the energies of two of
them may be negative.
the outgoing ones, each one of them
subject to this
constraint. The question that a
physicist would ask about this collision
is what is the amplitude? What is the
probability? The thing the amplitude is
a thing that you square the complex
number that you square to find the
probability for that collision. But the
collision is a function of a number of
variables.
It's a function or the probability for
the collision is a function of the
momenta of the incoming particles and a
function of the momentum of the outgoing
particles. So it's a function of the
k's. Let's call that amplitude a. It's a
thing that you square and it's a
function of all of the k's k1 k2 k3
k4. But there's some redundant
information here. First of all, the
momenta has to be conserved. Second of
all, the square of each k has to add up
to uh to minus the mass squared. So
there's really too many variables here.
There's too many independent variables.
How many independent variables are
there?
Uh before we impose any constraints,
each momentum has four variables. This
is four plus four is 8 + 4 is uh 12 +
four more is 16.
Okay, that's a lot of variables for
something to depend on. Fortunately, you
really don't depend on that many
variables. Let's think about physically
now. How many variables does a
scattering amplitude or scattering
process depend on? Well, the first thing
you can do is whatever the moment
are, you can use relativity to go to a
frame of reference where the center of
masses where the center of mass is at
rest. In other words, where the two
momenta the two space components of the
momentum are equal and opposite.
You can always do
that. If the particles are both moving
down the Z-axis, well, you just move
fast enough to be halfway in between
them. If they also happen to be moving
in some other direction, just move in
that direction. You can always go to a
frame of reference where the particles
are equal and
opposite the space components. In other
words, the spatial momenta.
Next, you can always rotate the system
so that the momenta are coming in along
the
x-axis. Okay, what's left over in the
initial state? What does it depend on?
If
you know that the momenta are equal and
opposite, what does the whole thing
depend on? It only depend what does the
initial state depend on? The initial
state only depends on the magnitude of
the momentum. Not the magnitude of the
square of the momentum. I mean sorry not
the magnitude of the four vector. The
four vector has to have magnitude m^
square but the but the magnitude of the
space
momentum or the energy if you like once
you go to the center of mass the only
thing left over is the total energy of
the collision in the center of mass
frame. Okay. So that's one thing. E
center of
mass. Now let's suppose that our
particles are all of the same kind for
simplicity. The particles
collide. What can you say about the
outgoing
momentum? First thing is they have to be
equal and
opposite. Why? That's momentum
conservation. Momentum conservation says
they have to be equal and opposite. What
about the energy of the outgoing state?
has to be the same as the energy of the
incoming state. What is the only thing
that can differ between the incoming and
the outgoing uh particles?
The angle. That's it. The angle of
scattering
theta. So the scattering amplitude
although it's written in terms of 16
variables really only depends on two two
independent
variables. Those variables should be
expressable in terms of relativistically
invariant things. Uh we can think of it
in the center of mass but we also be
ought to be able to think about it in
any frame of reference. We should be
able to construct two independent
invariants relativistic invariants which
are enough to completely characterize
the
scattering. So let's talk about the
invariance describing a scattering
process.
Two particles come in, two particles go
out. Let's think of them as all coming
in. Changing the sign of the momentum.
K, what is this? K1,
K2,
K3,
K4. All right. What can you do with a
four vector? What can you do with four
vectors to construct invariance?
There's only one thing you can do
really. You can square them. That's
about all you can do. But you don't have
to be talking about K1 squared or K2
squared. You could be talking about K1
plus K2 squared. Right? That's a good
invariant. K1 as a four vector. K1 + K2
K1 +
[Music]
K2 squared. Now remember what that
means. That means the space components
of K K1 plus K2 which I'll label with
arrows
squared minus the time component which
means the energies. Let's label them K
not K not means
energy K not one and K not 2 squared.
You sum the momenta square it you sum
the energies square it and subtract. And
that's called K1 + K2 squared. Let's see
if we can figure out what it
is. It's an invariant quantity. Let's
see if we can figure out what it is by
going to the center of mass
frame. In the center of mass frame, the
momentum of this
particle, what should we call it? Well,
it's K1. It's the space component
K1. What about the momentum of this
particle?
It's equal and opposite
minus K1. Right? So the total space
component of the momentum in the center
of mass frame is zero. We don't have to
worry about this
one. What about this one over
here? That's the
energies. We didn't talk about it, but
what about the energies of the two
particles in the center of mass frame?
They're equal and opposite. They have
the same mass. The energies are
equal. The center of mass frame is one
in which the particles are perceived as
moving with exactly the same momentum
magnitude of the momentum and so the two
energies are the same. So this just
becomes
twice
kantity squared.
Very simple. This is the center of mass
energy. Here in the center of mass
frame, you add the two energies. It's
the total energy and the square of it is
just the square of the center of mass
energy.
So this quantity
here which is called minus s it's just
called minus s is nothing but the square
of the center of mass
energy just look at it or s is the
center of mass energy.
Why in the center of mass frame this is
zero and this is just the total energy.
So minus S is just the square minus the
square of the center of mass
energy. Square of the center of mass
energy we call
S. Now can you think of any other
invariant that you can
build? How about K3 + K4 squared? We
took K1 plus K2 squared. How about K3
plus K4 squared?
The same thing. It's the same thing.
Why? because K1 + K2 is minus K3 + K4
energy conservation. So we don't get
anything new there. K1 + K2 squar is the
same as K3 + K4 2. It's the energy and
this just says that the energy in the
initial state is the same as the energy
in the final state. Okay. What about K1
+ K3
squared? That could be something new. So
let's see what it is. Let's see if we
can figure out what K1 + K3 squared is
by working in the center of mass
frame. In the center of mass frame, all
the particles in and out have the same
total energy. Have the same energy. Each
particle has the same energy. Particles
just get scattered through an angle.
That's all that happens. So they come in
and they go out with the same energy but
they scatter through an angle. Okay.
Um so let's take K1 + K3
squared. Ah here it is. K1 + K3 2 K3 2
K1 K3
2 How about this? What is this in the
center of mass frame?
K4.
It is K same as K2 and K4. But that
doesn't help. I want to know what it is
though. How big is it? All the particles
have the same
energy incoming and outgoing. All they
do is scatter through an angle.
Zero. Zero. Why is zero? Why not twice
K? Why not twice the energy?
Yeah, because K3 and
K4 we flipped the sign on them. All
right, so this isn't
there. And this is just K1 plus K3 squ.
So let's see if we can see what that
is. K1 comes in, particle one comes in
and of course also particle
2. Particle three goes out. Here's
particle three. One goes in, three goes
out. But if we label these particles
with the K's,
K1 and let's call this one now
Q Q3. Let's make it an outgoing
particle. Then really what this is is
it's
K1 minus
Q3 squared. It's really the difference
of the momentum of the incident particle
and the final particle. It's called the
momentum
transfer. It's the momentum transferred.
If you were to think
of particle one and particle three as
the same species of particle, then it
would just be in the collision. It's the
momentum transferred from one to three.
Bing bing. There's a momentum
transfer and that's the momentum
transferred from 1 to three. That's what
this is momentum transfer. It can also
be expressed in terms of the angle of
scattering. I will tell you what the
formula is. The
formula, the formula
for K1 + K3
squared is it's just
twice the energy squared minus the mass
squared. All right, we already worked
out what the what the energy is. The
energy is the S variable. It's twice
E^2us M^2 in the center of mass frame
times 1 minus the coine of the angle of
scattering. This is the interesting
thing here. The angle of scattering is
the angle between 1 and
three. All right, K1 comes in, Q3 goes
out, the particle gets deflected through
an angle and it's that deflection angle.
Here it is, theta, the deflection angle
of the
particle between the incoming state and
the outgoing state. And that's what's
here. Why is that interesting? Well, of
course, that's what's measured in an
experiment. You put detectors in
different places. You scatter particles
and you find out the probability for
them to get deflected to an angle at
different values of the energy.
this variable the K1 plus oh let's see
what did we do we I'm sorry we I uh
I the definition of S I forgot to erase
the S over here the definition of S was
K1 + K2
squared that was the definition of it 1
+ 2 coming in and it was the square of
the center of mass
energy so
S equals energy center of mass S
squared K1 + K3
squared. That's called Got another.
Anybody think up a name for it?
Te T. Good.
T. It is called T. I knew you were going
to get that.
And that
is some combination of the energy and
the momentum transfer. It's the center
of mass energy squared minus the mass
squared. Big deal. We already know what
the center of mass energy is. Times 1
minus cosine of the angle of
scattering. All right. So we have K1 +
K3 2. How about K2 plus K4 2?
Is that different?
Well, if you go back up to here, K1 + K3
is minus K2 + K4. So K1 + K2 2 is the
same as K3 + K4 squared. It's also T. Is
there another
combination? We have K1 plus K2. We have
K1 plus
K3. K1 plus K4, right? That's another
one. All right. So, the one more
quantity is K1 + K4
squared. What can that
be? Well, what if you were going to give
it a name, what would you call it? Oh,
minus minus T = K1 + K3 2.
U minus U equals that. These are the STU
variables. But what's going on here?
There are only two quantities that the
scattering depends on. Energy and angle
of
scattering. Well, we seem to have three
independent things. Well, the answer is
there are not three independent things.
If you use the momentum conservation and
you use the fact that each k^ squ is
m^2, what you'll find is that s + t + u
is equal to minus4 m^2 or something like
that. There's a constraint among them.
There are not three independent ones,
only two. These are the two
interesting quantities. The third one is
dependent on the other two.
Do you have to consider the vacuum at
all in these collisions? What does it
mean? Is the vacuum kind of
participating in the in the collisions?
Uh I'm not sure what that means. The
vacuum vacuums all over the place.
Participates like all hell. What does it
mean? Um what do you mean by
participate?
Well, maybe the vacuum could just slow
down a particle going through free space
or something. Well, well, we know that
doesn't happen, don't we? Okay. Yeah,
it's momentum conservation.
Okay. Well, just a wild idea. Yeah, it
could be. I mean, a possible world, a
vacuum has friction.
That's not our
world. Uh, momentum conservation says
that particles aren't slowed down by the
vacuum.
Uh
at some point I think you said that uh
Q3 and Q4 have the same energy
in the center of mass frame in the
center of mass. Why can't there be a I
mean K1 and K2 the center of mass frame
is kind of defined that way. Yeah. But
then the center of mass frame is defined
as a frame where the momenta are equal
and opposite. If the momenta are equal
and opposite the energies of the
particles are the same. if their masses
are the same. Now they scatter but they
have to go out equal and opposite for
momentum conservation reasons. Yeah. So
that's all right. These variables ST t
and U. The other one which is there
those are called mandle stam
variables and they're very symmetrically
defined. Mandle Stam. Mandal Stam.
Mandal
Stam. Mandal Stam is a currently uh
active physicist in Berkeley. But uh
this notation comes from the early 60s,
the very early 60s mandle stam
variables. And notice what that they
have. They have this beautiful symmetric
structure. That's what's interesting
about them. Now let's uh talk about
Fineman diagrams for a moment and I'll
just tell you what the answer is for
certain Fineman
diagrams.
Um let's
suppose two particles collide. This is a
Fineman diagram. Create a third particle
of a different mass in here. Let's call
it capital M. And then those particles
go out like this.
particles come
in a fineman diagram. So they come in
together, they coalesce to form a second
particle or a third particle or whatever
and then that particle decays and it
goes out. That's a Fineman diagram. That
Fineman diagram has a value. I'm going
to tell you what it is. It's the product
of two coupling
constants. There's always coupling
constants in Fineman diagrams. And then
there's the propagator of the particle
in between. And that has a very simple
form 1 / s minus capital m^
2. It has a is it? Yeah.
S minus capital m^
2. That's the characteristic structure
of a scattering amplitude where two
particles come together and merge and
form another particle. And notice it's a
function of s the energy proc the energy
of the process. It doesn't depend on t.
It doesn't depend on the other
uh variable. You want one that depends
on the other variable. You draw a
similar diagram except in which instead
of one and two merging, you have I'll
draw it over here. One and three
merging.
1 2 3 4. It looks like exactly the same
diagram except turned on its
side. But it represents a very different
uh kind of physical process. One and two
come in, exchange a particle between
them and then go out as three and four.
What would you guess if you had to guess
the amplitude for this process
is? It's going to have g^2 again. The
g's are the vertices. What else?
Exactly. 1 over t minus
m^2. Now you can imagine a third process
which would be 1 over u - m^2. It would
look like this. Uh one
uh let's see that it's a little hard to
draw.
One. It looks like this. One and four
merge. One and four merge. Little you
have to switch the lines like that.
Let's ignore it. It's there. It's there
and it's important. But uh it's too hard
to draw. I don't like drawing cross
perpendicular to the other two. You
know, they're not perpendicular. It's
just a question of which particles came
together. And I hate drawing cross lines
on the blackboard. So, we won't
But there is in principle there can be
another one. This one depends only on
the
energy doesn't depend on the angle of
scattering altogether. T contains the
angle of scattering. S is only a
function of the energy. That means that
when this process happens it to say that
it doesn't depend on the angle of
scattering means that every angle of
scattering is equal equally probable.
when the particles go in they have equal
probability of getting deflected through
any angle
whatever. Okay, that seems odd but that
is the property of this process and the
reason is very simple. The particles
come in from some direction they form
this compound state and then when they
decay they've forgotten which direction
they came in from. So they come in, they
form the composite and then when the
composite decays it decays at an
arbitrary angle uncorrelated to the
initial directions. That's this process
here. This one is different. It depends
on the energy but also on the angle of
scattering. This is the one that depends
on the angle of scattering. And if you
work it out, it's easy to see that it
favors forwards. It favors small angle
scattering. disfavors large
angles. So this one depends on angle and
this one depends. But notice how
similar the two expressions are. There's
a real symmetry between them. In fact,
if you interchange S and T, the
scattering doesn't change. This is a
property of relativistic scattering
amplitudes that they have this kind of
symmetry. they sort of forget which were
the incoming and which were the outgoing
particles but only if you express it in
terms of these kind of
invariance. Okay, good. So now we have
some basic idea of what it is that a
theoretical physicist wants to compute
about a model of particles to compare
not because he's so interested in it but
it's the thing that he can give to the
experimentalist and say measure the
probabilities for scattering as a
function of energy and so forth and
here's my prediction.
Okay. Are are you saying that the
dependence of
STNU causes this
amplitude to what? Shift around if you I
mean you still have three terms but
uh but the value shifts around if you uh
shift around as well depends on the
angle of
scattering. All right. So if all that
was there was
this, this would favor small angle
scattering and uh be uh not forbid but
make it less likely. Let's see if we can
see why. Oh, I think I here it is. I'm
just asking you have a third term. The
third term is there.
Uh what about it? Oh, well, but you say
that you didn't want to write it up
there or that it's you didn't want to
write the diagram. I didn't want to draw
the diagram, but if there was a process
in which one and four could come
together and do the same thing, then we
would want to put a g^2 one over t one
over uus m^2. And because the three are
not completely independent, yeah,
they're they're connected. Yeah.
The one over u Okay, so what is u? It's
interesting. U is equal to E center of
mass^ 2 - M^ 2 * 1 um 1 + cosine
theta. So both
uh so they're clearly
related. If you know S, you know the
energy. Therefore, if you also know T,
you know the angle of scattering. And
this is just a function of the energy
and the angle of scattering. So they're
all connected with each other. Another
way to say it is if you add S and U,
you'll cancel out the angle all together
and you'll get just a function of
energy
which is clearly dependent only on S.
Right. Right. But they're all but
they're separate fineman diagrams and in
general you have to you have to add them
all. Okay. But I want to focus on this
uh on this
here.
Um this does not describe
uh the scattering of mezison for example
very well. It gives a poor description
of the scattering of mezison. And the
reason is simple. The reason is that
there are many many different particles
that can be produced when two mezzons
collide. Whole stacks of them with
different mass and different angular
momentum. We haven't described what the
angular momentum would do here. What the
angular momentum would do would be to
change the dependence on the angle of
scattering. Let's not get into it. uh
formulas like this are too simple to
describe the realistic scattering of
mezons. It's too easy to
excite
higher vibrations of these particles
here.
And when two particles collide, they
could make some ground state, they could
make some first excited state, they
could make some next excited state. They
can make a whole raft of different
particles that can go in there.
And
um people in the
60s basically beginning sometime around
1965,667 tried to concoct
um mathematical amplitudes with
interesting mathematical
properties that would
represent all of the possible particles
which could go in here. This was trial
by uh you know trial and error. It was
um just making up formulas to try to
represent the different particles which
could go in here and different particles
which could go in here. The first
attempts tended to be to add particle.
This is called an S channel process.
Why? because it involves 1 / s - m^2
particles coming
[Music]
together k1
k2 that defines s this is called the t
channel
process k1 and k3 coming together so
they began by saying let's just add more
and more stuff into
here S channel and let's add more and
more stuff into here T channel for all
the particles that could uh that could
be
scattered. Well, that lasted for a
certain period of time adding up the
various particles which could go in
there. And then people tried to find
more comprehensive formulas just uh by
um I don't even know what the right word
is sort of a kind of curve fitting but a
very sophisticated kind of curve
fitting and a rather dramatic formula
was discovered which contained the
physics of all of the particles in the S
channel and all of the particles in the
T channel just replaced this combination
here with but not just one particle but
many of them whole towers of them with a
formula which I'm going to just this is
of historical interest mainly
uh with a formula which I will write
down and you can explore its beauty its
great
beauty
there's it's very very simple it's
called the venetsiano amplitude
Good then. Let's
see. Amplitude young Italian physicist.
He was young at the time. He's not young
anymore, but he's still
Italian. He just I I don't know how he
made this guess. He just he
just randomly wrote down some things
which had some right
properties and uh which really did look
like adding up things like this. It was
a function of
snamma function is
well the gamma function you don't need
to know it but I'm just going to write
down the formula for fun. The gamma
function is a generalization of the
factorial
function. But the factorial function is
only defined for
integers. The gamma function is defined
interpolated between integers. The gamma
function for the integers is equal to n
minus one factorial gamma of n. But it's
defined for non- integers too. But I
won't tell you. It's defined by an
integral and it continuously
interpolates between the
integers. This is it. This is the
veniano amplitude multiplied by the
coupling constant squared.
If you examine this amplitude, you'll
find out. I'm not going to go into its
mathematics. Its mathematics is very
simple. All you have to know is about
gamma functions. And I if you if you
want to explore it, it's it's actually
quite a simple construction. But I'm
going to tell you what it looks like. It
looks like an
amplitude that you would make by summing
up large number of particles. This is
representing some composite particle or
some particle that could be in there of
different masses in the S
channel. But it also looks like if oh
notice that it's it's it's symmetric.
It's symmetric with respect to S and T
exactly like this is. The peculiar thing
about it is you can represent it as a
kind of some refinement diagrams with
all the particles in the S channel
diagrams like this. But because it's
symmetric under S&T, you can also
represent it. You don't add it is also
equal to the same kind of thing going
this way.
Something odd was a foot about this
formula. It had all the important
features that the scattering amplitude
should have. It could be analyzed as if
a whole bunch of particles were produced
and then decayed. But it could also be
analyzed as if a whole bunch of
particles were
exchanged. This was something new. This
had not been seen
before. Previous to this everybody would
have added contributions for S&T and
this thing replaced
this. The question was what is this?
Where does this come from? What kind of
physics gives rise to this? What kind of
physics can you imagine would give rise
to
this to a formula like this?
The answer of course turned out to be
string
theory. The invention and the discovery
of string theory was just looking for a
physical model which would give this for
its answers for its answer for
scattering of uh two mezzons or two uh
two
particles. I'm going to tell you
uh without a lot
of
drama what physical model gives rise to
this scattering amplitude. And I'll show
you a little bit. I'll show you what the
logic that went into it
was. It wasn't very hard to guess that
this was a theory of strings. Uh it
wasn't too hard just
because
well it wasn't too
hard. So you said exchange particles
versus
uh this is you can the S channel and T
channel exchange um direct production
and
exchange sometimes called the direct
channel and the cross channel. The S
channel is called the direct channel.
Those are the direct particles come in,
coalesce and then go out. The cross
channel is when the particle jumps
across from one side to
another. All right, I'll show you what
the physics
uh of that formula
is. You begin with two
strings. I'm not going to do a
calculation, but I'll show you
everything that went into it.
It's a little bit uh a little bit
tedious. What you have to know about you
have to know a lot about harmonic
oscillators and that's all. Nothing much
more than that. You start with two
strings. All right. Here's a string. Now
remember the string has a coordinate
along it which we called sigma. Let's
draw the sigma axis over here from sigma
from zero to
pi. And here's the string. But the
string propagates in time. Let's draw
time horizontally. Here's the end of a
string at sigma equals
0. Sigma equals pi. These are open
strings. Now the string of course moves
around in spacetime but it's always
located between zero and pi. That's not
spatial position. That's just uh its
parameter along the
string. And the material of the string,
the particles that make it up
are in
here. Each point in the history of the
string, think of the string as sweeping
along. Here it is. It's sweeping along
some
space-time sheet. It's called a world
sheet instead of a world line. Each
point in that world sheet is
characterized by a point sigma and a
time which has called toao. Tao goes
this way. It's a time and sigma is a
coordinate along the string. Not a real
spatial coordinate, just a label for
labeling points along the string. Towel
is this time that we've used previously
uh the infinite momentum time. But
that's not what's important. What's
important is that the idea of a world
line becomes a world
sheet and instead of being parameterized
by a
single variable tow, it's now
parameterized by two
variables. Each point in
here has a position in spaceime x x mu
or just
x. And we've already worked out what the
equations of motion of X are. They are
the wave equations describing
waves moving up and down the string. The
wave equation, let's write it. It was
d2x da^ 2 minus
d2x d sigma^ 2 equals zero. That's the
wave equation that described the
oscillations of the string.
But we don't even have to think about
this. We can just imagine that this
string is a collection of a large number
of
particles replaced the world sheet by a
bunch of world lines narrowly spaced
with springs between
them with with springs between them.
That's the picture of the evolution of a
particle. Now, what we're going to do is
begin with two
particles. We're going to have two
particles coming
in from the past, and we're going to put
them right next to each other. Let's
see. I think we need another color for
the second particle. We're not going to
put them right next to each other in
space necessarily, but just in the
parameter space here. This goes from 0
to pi. We need to put another one in
going from pi also from uh from zero to
pi. Here's the other
string. There's no meaning to the fact
that I've drawn them right next to each
other. I've just drawn them. Their
actual position in spaceime might not be
adjacent. So, this just parameterizes
this half parameterizes the world sheet
of the left particle. This half
parameterizes the world sheet of the
right particle. And they might be far
away from each other. That means the x's
over here may be very different than the
x's over
here. But with any luck at
all, with some
probability, the end of the string might
touch the end of that string. And when
it
does, they can coalesce. That's an
assumption that they can coalesce. But
that's the basic process of string
theory that they can coalesce and then
form a single
string.
Now they really are
connected. If you like a new spring
developed when these touched each other
a spring appeared connecting the last
the last particle of this string with
the first particle of that string and
the whole thing becomes one string.
That condition persists for a
while. It persists for a while
until a quantum mechanical event happens
and the strings separate again
randomly. But uh you
can transform around cleverly to make it
be at the same place along the string.
There's enough symmetry enough symmetry
of the uh of the equations that you can
um put this point at the same point the
same horizontal level as this
point. So what do you have to so all
right so what is the nature of this
process?
Given
this, it's possible to guess what the
answer is for the O. The important
quantity in here is the amount of time
that the uh that the string spends
coalesed. It's the amount of time that
the compound state
stays before it breaks up into its final
constituents. Right? And let's just call
that tower. Now let's call that from
this this time here
toao. I'll tell you what we do with it
in the end. In the end we integrate over
it. But uh let me tell you what you put
in. If you're interested in a quantum
mechanical amplitude, you want to start
with an initial state. The initial
state, let's start with one particle.
The initial state, the initial state can
be thought of as the state of a whole
bunch of little points, namely the
points that make up the string x1
through xn. Let's start with the first
string x1 through
xn. It's just a collection of mass
points x1 dot dot dot through
xn. And the wave function of it is just
a function of x1 through xn.
That's its wave function to begin with
in the
start. Okay. What do we know about the
wave
function? Does everybody understand why
a wave function is a function of the end
positions of the
particles? That's quantum mechanics.
Quantum mechanics says wave functions or
state vectors are functions of the
position of the constituents.
What's the probability to find the
particles at position x1 through xn
si star s. So this is that's what this
is. This is the wave function of the
starting assemblage of particles. Of
course I'm I'm purposefully not taking
the continuum limit to show you what
goes on. The end you have to take the
continuum limit but let's not do that.
What do we know about this? Well, the
first thing we know about it is that
this particle comes in with momentum
K1. I'll tell you exactly what that
says. That says that this wave function
contains a
factor e to the i
k1 times the center of mass position.
This is the wave the wave function e to
the i kx is the wave function of a
particle with definite momentum. What
momentum do you use? You use the center
of mass momentum. So what is the center
of mass position? Sorry, the center of
mass position. What's the center of mass
position of these
points? It's the average position. X1,
the sum of the x's divided by n. So you
have x1 + x2 dot dot dot up to
xn divided by n.
That factor and that factor alone tells
you that this initial particle here had
momentum
K1. Now what about the rest of the wave
function which depends on the relative
coordinates? Not the sum of them but the
distances between the neighboring
particles. That's some wave function
which characterizes the ground state. It
depends on everything except the sums of
the
x's. It's some wave
function. Let's call it s not for ground
state. And it depends on the x's. Same
x's. But it actually doesn't depend on
the sum of them. The sum of them here,
the differences between them here.
Differences of x's here. They bringing
x's and so forth here. Some of them
here. And this wave function is
computable. It's just the ground state
describing the ground state of all the
harmonic oscillators making up the uh
the string. And you can really work it
out. That can you know with enough with
enough room on the blackboard I could
tell you exactly what this function is
as a function of a collection of x's.
It's not very hard. It's a bunch of uh
bunch of exponentials. It's workable.
You can do it. This is the wave function
of the first particle. What about the
wave function of the second particle?
It's exactly the same kind of thing
except it doesn't depend on these
coordinates. It depends on the
coordinates of the red particles here.
So let's write it
down. It's e to the i
k2.
Now what shall I write? Shall I write x1
through
xn? No. That's the original particle of
those those are the original
constituents of the first string. I want
the constituents of the second string.
So let's write x n
+1 x n + 2 all the ways up to x to
n. The second half of the particles is
grouped together into the second string
also divided by
n also times s
of 1 through
n. This is x n + one to the end to the
end of the chain. Can that be read? It
is
red but can you read it?
Okay, you can read it. Now that's the
initial state. But now you say with some
probability the two end points
merge. To say that the two end points
merge simply
says that you set x1 sorry xn equal to
xn + one. You look for that piece of the
wave function where the two end points
are at exactly the same
point. So you begin with this. The next
step is to say let the nth particle on
the first chain be at exactly the same
place as the n plus sorry as the x n
being at the same place as xn plus one.
All right. That's what we're going to
put in here. Then
XN all the others left
unchanged. That's now not that's the
wave function of the state right at the
point after the two particles have
coalesed. When they're coalesed, at the
point where they coalesed, they come
together. Nothing happens to the rest of
the chain but the two
particles. So this is if you like it's
the amplitude that the two particles the
chain touched. This is the amplitude
that the two particles the end points
touched. Now we have a new starting
point which is a function of
x1 through
x2n. It's a state of that many
particles. And what do we do with it? We
have to evolve it. We have to evolve it
using the Hamiltonian. Remember what a
Hamiltonian is? A Hamiltonian is a thing
which updates you from one instant to
the next. So you take this initial
state. It's a well- definfined thing and
you propagate it forward in time using
the
Hamiltonian. You take
it. What's the right rule for updating a
state from one from an instant to a
later instant? You multiply the state by
something. E to the
iH E to the I. So you take this wave
function and you evolve it. You solve
the Schroinger equation for it. But
that's the same as multiplying it by E
to the I the total Hamiltonian times
tow. But what is the total Hamiltonian?
The total Hamiltonian is only it's just
the collection of springs and mass
points. A collection of harmonic
oscillators. It's just a collection of
harmonic oscillators. We know how to do
this. And that gives us the state of the
system after time
t. What's the last step? The last step
is to project the final state. Here it
is onto two separate particles. again to
project it onto a state with two
separated particles of momentum K3 and
K4. It's very very straightforward if
tedious, slightly tedious. You take the
two initial states of the two particles,
they're well-defined ground states of
the particles. You insist
that the two end points are at the same
place. that constrains the wave
function. You let it evolve as a single
string for a wave and then you let it
break up again. And that simply means
multiplying it again by some final
state. I'm not going to write it all
out. It's the same kind of
thing. And that gives you the transition
amplitude. To make a long story short,
you start with the two particles, you
constrain it so that they're at the same
place. you evolve it and then you
project it onto the final state. A very
very well- definfined thing to do that
gives you the
amplitude that the strings coalesed for
an amount of time
towo. But how should you choose to?
Those the things in black and red there
are added together and then you multiply
those are multiplied together. Yeah. If
you have two separate systems each
having its own wave function, you
multiply to create the wave function of
a composite. So this is just a wave
function of a composite of two
particles to begin with. You don't set
the first particle equal to the last
particle
here. Then you look for the amplitude.
You look for the piece of the wave
function where those two particles are
at the same place. You say, "Aha, now
that they're at the same place, fuse
them together and evolve it as if it
were a single
string, a single collection of mass
points and
springs for an amount of time tow. And
then basically you take your scissor and
just cut the uh you cut the spring in
the middle and let it evolve. After
that, that calculation is quite doable.
Not even very hard. It's just too much
for the blackboard for uh for one for
one evening. But I'm going to tell you
what the answer
is. I'm going to write down the answer
for
you. Don't don't try to remember this.
This is the answer. It's an integral
over d towo. Did we say that we
integrate over to? I think I said we
integrate. Why do we integrate over
toao?
Incidentally, why do we add up the
amplitudes for all possible times that
this composite could
exist? This is the fineman rule of
summing over all possibilities.
The only parameter here is the time that
it takes for this uh for this to break
up again. And Fineman's rule is sum over
all paths which in this case just means
integrate over the time that they spent
uh evolving together. And that gives you
the amplitude for particle for the two
particles in the initial state to become
the two particles in the final state.
The result is an integral. It's the
integral over the time that they spend
together. That's it. All right. I'll
tell you what the integrant is
after a certain amount of calculation,
which is actually not very hard. It
becomes the integral of e to the tow.
That's the
times s + one. This s + one is exactly
this s. It's the s variable or the
center of mass squared or center of mass
energy of the two
particles. You have a factor like that.
You have another factor which is 1 - e
to the
tow the minus t minus
one. t is the momentum change between
the initial particle here and the final
particle
here. Remember those momenta are coded
in this wave function which I've erased.
They were coded in the wave function in
terms of those exponentials.
initial moment uh sorry the center mass
energy and here is the momentum transfer
it appears in the formula and then you
have to integrate it d
to there happens to be another factor I
think of e to the minus toao in the
integrant dice you're right I have da
twice e to the minus yeah
The first term is to * s + one.
Yeah. No. Uh,
yes. Yeah. That's what you get. Is that
plus e to the minus tow or what's that?
When you combine the e to the minus tow
hanging out the end, is that multiplied
or added? It multiplies this, but I've
left it I've left it out here on
purpose. I left that out here on
purpose. The
towel. Now, that doesn't look
particularly symmetric between toao and
between t and
s. But after it was computed, it took
about uh a half hour to realize that you
should change variables in this
integral.
change variables from e to the tow from
toao to something called z. Let e to the
tow equals
z. Okay, let e to the tow equals
z. And now rewrite
this e to the tow is z. So this becomes
integral of z
uh I'm missing some minus sign. No e e
to the minus uh e to the minus towel
must be uh
This must be minus
here. It is e to the minus tow. There
um this thing just becomes
z to the s + one uh to the minus s +
one e to the minus to. So this is minus
minus e to the minus to z by definition
just a change of variables. What about 1
- e^ the minus to that becomes 1 -
z to the minus to minus
one. Oh, incidentally this integral goes
I think from zero to
infinity. Is that right? From
0 to infinity. Yes, it does. All right.
This becomes 1 minus z to the minus to
minus 1. What is d tow * e to the minus
toao h? It's just dz. It's just
dz. I think I got
it. It's just dz or
my did I get that
right? I've lost track of whether this
is plus or minus here. I I don't
remember. But it's just dz. This is the
formula. And where does the integral go?
The integral goes from toao equals
0 where z is equal to
1 to this is minus. It is minus. I'm
sorry I'm I'm making a mess out of it. E
to the minus tow is equal to z to tow
equals infinity. In other words, you
have towel equals zero. That's when it
very
suddenly merges and then falls apart
instantly. The tow equals infinity when
the separation is infinite here. And
what happens when tow goes to infinity?
Z goes to zero. So it's an integral from
1 to 0 or 0 to one. There's probably
some sign in here. Uh of an integral
that looks like this.
The amazing thing about this integral,
the whole upshot of it is that this
integral is completely symmetric between
S and T. Can you see
that? How do you see that it's symmetric
between S and
T? Right? You just substitute for Z
minus one. You make a change of
variables between Z and Z minus one. And
you see that this integral is completely
symmetric.
So although a completely unsymmetric
starting point between energy and
momentum transfer somehow it wound up
giving a completely symmetric answer
between the two of them. The minus sign
I I lost track of the minus sign comes
from e to the minus toa d to going to
dz.
Yeah. Um I've lost track of the uh so
you get a minus sign. That's why you
switch to the order. There's a minus
sign somewhere. I'm saying e to the
minus tow d tow. Yes. And then you're
going to make that just be dz. Yes. So
you get a minus sign. Yeah. There's got
to be a minus sign out here. Right.
Right. Then you switch the order. Then
you switch the order of integration and
it becomes from zero to one like this.
That's right. That's correct. It's
symmetric whether or not you switch the
order of
integration. Right. And
that's that's the answer. It's symmetric
between S and T. And what is it? It's a
process in which two particles join,
form a composite which wiggles around
for a while and then breaks up. In other
words, it's the analog of the Fineman
diagram in which a composite is formed
and then decays.
composite is formed and then
decays. But it winds up being completely
symmetric between S and T. In fact, this
function is called the Oiler beta
function. It's a function of two
variables S and T. It's called
beta of minus S and minus
T. It's the Oiler beta function.
It's a famous function of mathematical
physics. And guess what it's equal to?
It's equal to the viniano amplitude.
It's exactly equal to the vinitiano
amplitude, namely this product of gamma
functions over another gamma
function. Um, how did it get to be that
it was symmetric between the two? Now
this is not obvious at all that it's
symmetric between the S channel and the
T channel completely symmetric between
the S channel and the T channel. I'm
going to come to that next time. That
has to do with a fundamental extremely
deep symmetry of string theory called
conformal
symmetry. It's a symmetry which allows
you to take these world sheets and
deform them in crazy ways as if they
were Turkish taffy and stretch them out
in different directions.
And for example, turn this
picture into a picture which looks much
more
like two particles coming together and
exchanging
something. It's a character. Yeah. So
the gamma gamma over gamma function is
reminiscent of the probability function
of
uh I think it's factorial a factorial b
over factorial a permutation right
coefficients yeah so what's what's the
timing between the two or just
coincidence it is true that uh that the
beta function evaluated at integers
uh is the combinatoric coefficient the
inverse of the combinatorial
coefficients. You know what he's talking
about? He's talking about um n
factorial m factorial over n plus m
factorial which occurs all over the
place in combinotaurics.
No just happens to be the same function.
No simple no simple
um no simple connection.
uh first of all it's the inverse of it.
The inverse of it is not a combinatoric
coefficient. Uh but
um just happens it's an integral which
defines the same combination of gamma
functions. There is no simple uh uh
relationship. It's not that something
combinatoric went on here. At least not
not to my knowledge and it's certainly
not the way Venitziano found
it. I don't know what magic he pulled up
to find it. Um so this was if you like
partly historical but um part of the
important logic of the theory is that
number one you can calculate with it.
It's all it is is harmonic oscillators.
Anything can be done with harmonic
oscillators.
Uh it's a bunch of harmonic oscillators.
You break the process up into
pieces and then you integrate over the
time in between. You can calculate. You
calculate and you find an integral. The
integral by at this point by magic has
the property that it's symmetric between
s and t and somehow looks
like not the sum but has the features of
having processes where particles coales.
That's the direct process I drew here.
But somehow buried in it is also somehow
processes where particles are
exchanged. And that was the magic of it.
That was the
surprise that um a whole new logic of
putting processes together to make new
processes. Okay. Um any questions about
this? Yeah. Um I think I'm missing
something. In in the beginning when you
describe two strings coalesing you have
a string on n oscillators and n o
oscillators they come together two n
bzons
but remember when you're taking the
limit n goes to infinity to land is the
same as n sure but but it still has the
property of bzon firm oh yes so far yeah
but the question is when you wrote down
the wave equation you had the two points
coalescing which is 2n minus one So it
changes from positive. It seems
inconsistent. I'm sure you lose you lose
two, not one.
Well, n and n plus one becomes one. No,
actually in n plus one disappear
basically. Okay.
If you like. I mean, I think that's the
right way to think about it. You Yeah.
Uh
yeah, they eat each other. They eat each
other like that. And you're left with
Right. So, so the new spring the new
spring that forms connects these two.
Yeah. Yeah. Otherwise, otherwise we'd
have big trouble. We would lose one
firm. Right. Right. So, that's a good
uh one way to think about it is that um
a particle and an antiparticle coalesed.
And uh if you thought of these as quarks
on ends of strings, you could think of
the last one being a quark which
annihilated with the first quark of the
uh of the other
string. So yeah, you lose two of them,
but who cares about two when there's an
infinite number? Yeah.
Right. Right. But you're right. You have
to be careful not to lose an odd number
of firmians. That's that's something
that shouldn't happen.
Yes. Uh next next quarter you continue
on with print theory and talk about uh
super strings.
Well, we're not going to spend a lot of
time on super strings. Um although the
things that I will tell you strictly
speaking apply to superstrings
um and not to the bosonic string. Are we
going? No, I am not going to go I'm into
the heavy mathematics of uh super
strings. What I think we're going to do
next time is I'm going to tell you well
I'll tell you a little bit more about
string theory and about the properties
of world sheets and the symmetries that
allow you to stretch this thing like
Turkish taffy and make different kinds
of fineman diagrams out of it. But then
we're going to move on to another
subject called M theory which is another
way of deriving string theory from a
totally different van. Well, I think we
have to talk a little bit about
compactification about what you do with
these extra dimensions and we will maybe
next time. Uh but then we will move on
to a totally different origin of string
theory
that evolved much much later in time
sometime around 199596.
uh which started with a completely
different picture and in which a great
many of the features the more
complicated features of string theory
are completely transparent and uh it's
called M theory and we'll we'll start a
different starting point which leads to
exactly the same uh the same physics.
Okay. Yeah. So this process that you
just described was based on the clues
from two masons colliding. Yes. But it's
also the way two photons collide in
string theory. It's the way any two open
strings collide in string theory.
Incidentally the analog for closed
strings is very similar.
You have two closed
strings
and you pick a particle from here and
one from here and you require that they
be at the same point so that they do
this kind of
thing and then you evolve it as a single
string. Same rules, same kind of
rules and that would correspond to the
scattering of two closed strings. If you
scatter two closed strings, the
intermediate thing that you make will
again be a closed string.
Does this only apply to strings where
the particles are firmians? No, no, no,
no, no, no, no, no. This the this this
calculation was originally done for the
bzonic uh string and and of course it's
more complicated when you have to keep
track of the firmians also. But you get
the same extremely similar extremely
similar some slight uh differences that
are not important.
Right? What I should say about this is
that the scattering amplitudes we said
that there was a photon and a um and a
graviton in the system. All right. It
looked like there was a spin two
particle and a spin one particle and you
could force them to be massless if you
wanted. You didn't have much choice.
There weren't enough components to make
a massive particle. So you did that.
Well, then you take these particles and
you collide them and you work out
scattering
amplitudes. Scattering amplitudes are
very distinctive and characteristic for
emission of photons and gravitons. They
are not just any old uh scattering
amplitudes. They have very very definite
properties which uh make them extremely
special. The emission and the emission
and absorption of photons cannot be
mistaken for the emission and absorption
of scalar particles or other things.
They they satisfy some very very
important rules. Those rules originate
from the conservation of electric
charge. conserved electric charges
emitting
photons. There's almost very very little
ambiguity in what the emission and
absorption of photons look like or what
a scattering of photons by charged
particles look like or even the
scattering of photons by photons. And it
was at this point calculating these
diagrams where it became completely
clear that these things which we were
calling photons were behaving exactly
like photons and the things that we were
calling gravitons were behaving exactly
like
gravitons that they satisfied all the
rules for graviton graviton scattering.
Just saying there was a particle that
looked like a graviton was a very weak
thing. When all of the scatterings were
constructed and the rigorous tests of
whether it was satisfying the rules for
scattering of gravitons by massive
things, by massless things and so forth
fit perfectly exactly. Then people
realized that they really were dealing
with something that looked like the
scattering of gravitons and photons.
So these scattering amplitudes played a
big role in establishing with uh you
know precision that we were dealing with
objects that did behave like photons,
gravitons and
uh
uh it
okay I think we're finished. Yes.
Well, where does charge come? Where's
what charge? Charge. Yeah, we haven't
talked about that, but
uh Okay, we'll talk we'll talk about it
next time. Remind me. Remind me.
For more, please visit us at
stanford.edu.